A Finding Aid to the Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney Papers, 1851-1975, bulk 1888-1942, in the Archives of American Art AAA.whitgert
Archives of American Art
- Artwork, 1871-1930s; Series 11; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 32, 41, OVs 52-54
  - Sketches by Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, 1891-1930s; 11.1
    Sketches have been scanned in entirety.
    - Sketchbooks (Box 32)
      - Early Sketches, 1891 (Box 32, Folder 15)
      - "Rough Sketches - The Story of Modern Girl,", 1890s (Box 32, Folder 16)
      - Figure Studies, Other Sketches, and Notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 17)
      - Anatomical Drawings, undated (Box 32, Folder 18)
      - Studies for Titanic Memorial, Other Sketches, and Writings, circa 1912 (Box 32, Folder 19)
      - Sketches for Sculptures, 1910s-1920s (Box 32, Folder 20-21)
      - "My Experience as an Emergency Canteen Worker,", circa 1916-1918 (Box 32, Folder 22-23)
    - Loose Sketches (Box 32)
      - Early Sketches, circa 1890s (Box 32, Folder 24)
      - Sketches, circa 1900s-1920s (Box 32, Folder 25-26)
      - Sketches for Sculptures, 1920s-1930s (Box 32, Folder 27-28)
      - Sketches for Museum and Play (?), undated (Box 32, Folder 29)
      - Fragments of Sketches of Sculptures, undated (Box 32, Folder 30)
    - Renderings of Sculptures, by Whitney and Others, circa 1920s (Box 32, Folder 31)
      Oversized material housed in OV 52
    - Oversize, Sketches for Sculpture scanned with Box 32, Folder 28, 1920s-1930s (Box 41)
    - Oversize, Renderings of Sculptures, by Whitney and Others scanned with Box 32, Folder 31, circa 1920s (Box OV 52)
  - Artwork by Others, 1871-1916; 11.2
    This subseries consists of etchings of Buffalo Bill, a sketchbook of Howard Cushing's which includes a sketch of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, albums of World War I lithographs, sketches by L. Feuchter and other unidentified artists, and a drawing (artist unknown).
    Artwork by others has been scanned in entirety.
    - Etchings of Buffalo Bill, 1871 (Box 32, Folder 32)
    - Sketchbook of Howard Cushing (includes sketch of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney), 1908 (Box 32, Folder 33)
    - World War I Lithographs (Box 32)
      - "Les Grandes Vertus Francaises" by L. Jonas, circa 1915 (Box 32, Folder 34)
        Oversized material housed in OV 53
      - "Album de 12 Lithographs: Nos Blesses, Nos Infirmieres" (incomplete), 1916 (Box 32, Folder 35)
        Oversized material housed in OV 54
      - "Une Journee a L'Hopital" by Louise Ibels (incomplete), 1916 (Box 32, Folder 36)
      - Lithograph by Steinlen, undated (Box 32, Folder 37)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 32, Folder 38)
    - Drawing (artist unknown), undated (Box 32, Folder 39)
    - Oversize, Drawing (artist unknown) scanned with Box 32, Folder 29, undated (Box OV 52)
    - Oversize, World War I Lithographs, "Les Grandes Vertus Francaises" by L. Jonas scanned with Box 32, Folder 34, circa 1915 (Box OV 53)
    - Oversize, "Album de 12 Lithographs: Nos Blesses, Nos Infirmieres," scanned with Box 32, Folder 35, 1916 (Box OV 54)
    - Oversize, "Une Journee de L'Hopital" by Louise Ibels scanned with Box 32, Folder 36, 1916 (Box OV 54)
    - Oversize, Lithograph by Steinlen scanned wiht Box 32, Folder 37, undated (Box OV 54)
- Blueprints, 1913-1945; Series 12; 0.1 Linear feet OV 55
  This series consists of plans and other drawings for Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney's studio on Macdougal Alley, for various sculptures, for the Whitney Museum of American Art, for the boat, "Sagamore," for the Vanderbilt Gates plaque, and for the Whitney Wing of the Metropolitan Museum of American Art.
  Blueprints have not been scanned due to size.
  Blueprints are arranged in chronological order.
  - Studio at West 8th Street and Macdougal Alley, 1913 (Box OV 55)
  - Gertrude V. Whitney Sculpture (Box OV 55)
    - Arlington Fountain, 1923 (Box OV 55)
    - Titanic Memorial, 1930; 1924-1926 (Box OV 55)
    - Buffalo Bill Memorial, 1929 (Box OV 55)
    - Rumsey Memorial, 1936 (Box OV 55)
    - Spirit of Flight, 1938 (Box OV 55)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, circa 1930 (Box OV 55)
  - Alteration to "Sagamore", 1936 (Box OV 55)
  - Study for Plaque for Vanderbilt Gates, 1938 (Box OV 55)
  - Whitney Wing, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1945 (Box OV 55)